<chapter>
<title>Internals: hosts, modules, threads</title>

	<para>This chapter describes the major internal components
	of the gateway and their interaction in general terms.</para>

	<!-- XXX fix image: add phones, c/m/c, don't show box internals -->

	<figure>
	<title>Major gateway components</title>
	<graphic fileref="arch-components&figtype;"></graphic>
	</figure>
	
	<para>The gateway will divide the processing load on several
	hosts, which are of three different types:
	
	<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Bearer box
		</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>This host connects to the SMS centers and CSD
		routers, and provides a unified interface to them for
		the other boxes. It implements the WDP layer of the
		WAP stack.  </para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>WAP box
		</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>These hosts run the upper layers of the WAP stack.
		Each session and the transactions that belong to that
		session are handled by the same WAP box. Sessions and
		transactions are not migrated between WAP boxes.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>SMS box
		</term>
		<listitem>
		<para>These hosts run the SMS gateway. They can't connect
		directly to the SMS centers, because the same SMS center
		connection can be used for both SMS services and WAP.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</para>
	
	<note><para>There can, in this design, only be one bearer box, but
	any number of the other boxes. (This is a potential performance
	bottleneck, and will be dealt with later.)</para></note>

	<para>The bearer box receives SMS messages from SMS
	centers, inspects them to see whether they are plain
	SMS messages or contain WAP packets, and then routes
	them to the appropriate kind of box. It keeps track
	of the WAP and SMS boxes that are currently running,
	and routes all messages from a particular terminal to
	the same box. Similarly, it receives UDP packets from
	CSD routers and routes them to the boxes based on the
	sender. This simple design allows the bearer box to
	do as little processing as possible per packet, which
	reduces its bottleneck karma. </para>
	
	<para>The bearer box also sends the SMS messages and
	UDP packets that the other boxes generate. This adds
	some more routing processing.</para>
	
	<para>The WAP boxes implement the WTP (transaction) and
	WSP (session) layers (and the WTSL security layer in the
	future). These take HTTP-like requests from the phones, and
	make the actual HTTP requests to content servers, compress
	the response, and send it back to the terminals. (Sessions are
	needed to make as much use of the limited radio bandwidth as
	possible.)</para>
	
	<para>The SMS boxes implement traditional SMS services: SMS messages
	with keywords and arguments are translated into URLs and the
	corresponding HTML pages are stripped of markup and sent to the
	phone.</para>
	
</chapter>
