<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V3.1//EN"
     "dtd/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY figtype "#FIGTYPE#">
<!ENTITY timestamp "#DATE#">
]>
-->

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V3.1//EN"
     [
<!ENTITY figtype "#FIGTYPE#">
<!ENTITY timestamp "#DATE#">
<!ENTITY version "#VERSION#">
]>

<book>

<bookinfo>
	<title>Kannel &version; User's Guide</title>
	<subtitle>Open Source WAP and SMS gateway</subtitle>
	<author>
		<firstname>Lars</firstname>
		<surname>Wirzenius</surname>
		<affiliation>
			<jobtitle>Gateway architect</jobtitle>
			<orgname>Wapit Ltd</orgname>
			<address> <email>liw@wapit.com</email>
			<otheraddr>http://www.wapit.com</otheraddr>
			<otheraddr>http://www.kannel.org</otheraddr>
			</address>
		</affiliation>
	</author>
	<author>
		<firstname>Kalle</firstname>
		<surname>Marjola</surname>
		<affiliation>
			<jobtitle>Manager</jobtitle>
			<orgname>Wapit Ltd</orgname>
			<address> <email>rpr@wapit.com</email>
			<otheraddr>http://www.wapit.com</otheraddr>
			<otheraddr>http://www.kannel.org</otheraddr>
			</address>
		</affiliation>
	</author>
	<abstract>
		<title>Abstract</title> 
		<para>This document describes how
		to install and use Kannel, the Open Source WAP and SMS Gateway
		produced by Wapit Ltd.
		</para>
	</abstract>
</bookinfo>


<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>

	<highlights>
	<para>This chapter introduces WAP in general terms, and explains the
	role of the gateway in WAP, outlining its duties and features. It
	also explains why the Kannel project was started in the first place,
	and why it is open source.</para>
	</highlights>
	
	<para>With hundreds of millions of mobile phones in use all over the
	world, the market for services targeted at mobile users
	is mind-bogglingly immense.  Even simple services find plenty of users,
	as long as they're useful or fun. Being able to get news, send e-mail
	or just be entertained wherever you are is extremely attractive to
	many.</para>

	<para>The hottest technology for implementing mobile services is WAP,
	short for Wireless Application Protocol. It lets the phone act
	as a simple web browser, but optimizes the markup language,
	scripting language, and the transmission protocols for wireless
	use. The optimized protocols are translated to plain old HTTP by
	a <emphasis>WAP gateway</emphasis>.</para>

	<para>Kannel is an open source WAP gateway. It attempts to
	provide this essential part of the WAP infrastructure freely
	to everyone so that the market potential for WAP services,
	both from wireless operators and specialized service providers,
	will be realized as efficiently as possible.</para>

	<para>Kannel also works as an SMS gateway for GSM networks. Almost
	all GSM phones can send and receive SMS messages, so this is
	a way to serve many more clients than just those using a new
	WAP phone.</para>

	<para><ulink url="http://www.opensource.org">Open Source</ulink>
	is a way to formalize the principle of openness by placing the
	source code of a product under a Open Source compliant software
	license. The BSD license was chosen over other Open Source
	licenses by the merit of placing the least amount of limitations
	on what a third party is able to do with the source code. In
	practice this means that Kannel is going to be a fully-featured
	WAP implementation and compatible with the maximum number of
	bearers with special emphasis on SMSC compatibility.
	The Kannel project was founded by <ulink
	url="http://www.wapit.com">Wapit Ltd.</ulink> in June,
	1999.</para>
	
	
<sect1>
<title>Overview of WAP</title>

	<para>WAP, short for Wireless Application Protocol, is a
	collection of various languages and tools and an infrastructure for
	implementing services for mobile phones. Traditionally such
	services have worked via normal phone calls or short textual
	messages (e.g., SMS messages in GSM networks). Neither are very
	efficient to use, nor very user friendly.  WAP makes it possible
	to implement services similar to the World Wide Web.</para>
	
	<para>Unlike marketers claim, WAP does not bring the existing
	content of the Internet directly to the phone. There are too many
	technical and other problems for this to ever work properly. The
	main problem is that Internet content is mainly in the form of
	HTML pages, and they are written in such way that they require
	fast connections, fast processors, large memories, big screens,
	audio output and often also fairly efficient input mechanisms.
	That's OK, since they hopefully work better for traditional
	computers and networks that way. However, portable phones have
	very slow processors, very little memory, abysmal and intermittent
	bandwidth, and extremely awkward input mechanisms. Most existing
	HTML pages do not work on mobiles phones, and never will.</para>
	
	<para>WAP defines a completely new markup language, the Wireless
	Markup Language (WML), which is simpler and much more strictly
	defined than HTML.  It also defines a scripting language,
	WMLScript, which all browsers are required to support. To make
	things even simpler for the phones, it even defines its own
	bitmap format (Wireless Bitmap, or WBMP).</para>
	
	<para>HTTP is also too inefficient for wireless use. However, by using
	a semantically similar binary and compressed format it
	is possible to reduce the protocol overhead to a few bytes per
	request, instead of the usual hundreds of bytes. Thus, WAP defines a
	new protocol stack to be used. However, to make things simpler
	also for the people actually implementing the services, WAP
	introduces a gateway between the phones and the servers providing
	content to the phones.</para>

        <figure>
        <title>Logical position of WAP gateway between a phone and a content server.</title>
        <graphic fileref="wap-gateway&figtype;"></graphic>
        </figure>

	<para>The WAP gateway talks to the phone using the WAP protocol
	stack, and translates the requests it receives to normal
	HTTP. Thus content providers can use any HTTP servers and
	utilize existing know-how about HTTP service implementation
	and administration.</para>
	
	<para>In addition to protocol translations, the gateway
	also compresses the WML pages into a more compact form, to
	save on-the-air bandwidth and to further reduce the phone's
	processing requirements. It also compiles WMLScript programs
	into a bytecode format.</para>
	
	<para>Kannel is not just a WAP gateway. It also works as an
	SMS gateway.  Although WAP is the hot and technically superior
	technology, SMS phones exist in huge numbers and SMS services are
	thus quite useful. Therefore, Kannel functions simultaneously
	as both a WAP and an SMS gateway.</para>

</sect1>
	
	
<sect1>
<title>Features</title>

	<para>This section needs to be written.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Requirements</title>

	<para>Kannel is being developed on Linux systems (Red Hat 6.1 and
	Debian potato), and should be fairly easy to export to other Unix-like
	systems. However, we don't yet support other platforms, due to lack
	of time. Kannel requires the following software environment:
	
	<itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para>C compiler, development libraries and related
	tools.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>The Gnome XML library (known as
	gnome-xml and libxml), version 2.2.0 or newer. See <ulink
	url="http://xmlsoft.org/xml.html">http://xmlsoft.org/xml.html</ulink>.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>GNU Make.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Posix threads (pthread.h).</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>GNU Bison 1.28 if you modify the WMLScript
	compiler.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>DocBook markup language tools (jade, jadetex,
	DocBook stylesheets, etc; see README.docbook), if you want
	to format the documentation (pre-formatted versions are
	available).</para></listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>Hardware requirements are fluffier. We haven't benchmarked Kannel
	yet, so there are no hard numbers, but a reasonably fast PC workstation
	(400 MHz Pentium II, 128 MB RAM) should serve several concurrent
	users without problems. The goal is to support hundreds of concurrent
	users on that kind of hardware.</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Installing the gateway</title>

	<para>This chapter explains how the gateway can be installed,
	either from a source code package or by using a pre-compiled
	binary version. The goal of this chapter is to get the gateway
	compiled and all the files in the correct places; the next
	chapter will explain how the gateway is configured.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Getting the source code</title>

	<para>The source code to
	Kannel is available for download at <ulink
	url="http://www.kannel.org/download.shtml">http://www.kannel.org/download.shtml</ulink>.
	It is available in various formats and you can choose to download
	either the latest release version or the daily snapshot of the
	development source tree for the next release version, depending
	on whether you want to use Kannel for production use or to
	participate in the development.</para>
	
	<para>If you're serious about development, you probably want to
	use CVS, the version control system used by the Kannel project.
	This allows you to participate in Kannel development much
	more easily than by downloading the current daily snapshot and
	integrating any changes you've made every day. CVS does that
	for you. (See the Kannel web site for more information on how
	to use CVS.)</para>

</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>Finding the documentation</title>

	<para>The documentation for Kannel consists of three parts:
	
	<orderedlist>
	<listitem><para><citetitle>User's Guide</citetitle>, i.e., the one
		you're reading at the moment.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para><citetitle>Architecture and 
		Design</citetitle>, in <filename>doc/arch</filename> or
		at <ulink url="http://www.kannel.org/arch.shtml">
		http://www.kannel.org/arch.shtml</ulink></para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>The <filename>README</filename> and various other
		text files in the source tree.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	
	We intend to cover everything you need to install and use Kannel
	is in <citetitle>User's Guide</citetitle>, but the guide is still incomplete in this respect. Similarly, the <citetitle>Architecture and
	Design</citetitle> document should tell you everything you need
	to know to dive into the sources and quickly make your own modifications. It's not a replacement for actually
	reading the source code, but it should work as a map to the
	source code.  The <filename>README</filename> is not supposed
	to be very important, nor contain much information. Instead,
	it will just point at the other documentation.
	</para>
	
	<para>You need the following tools to compile Kannel:
	
	<itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para>C compiler and libraries for ANSI C, with normal
	Unix extensions such as BSD sockets.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>An implementation of POSIX threads
	(<filename>pthread.h</filename>).</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>GNU Bison 1.28, if you want to modify the WMLScript
	compiler (a pre-generated parser is included for those who just
	want to compile Kannel).</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>DocBook processing tools: DocBook stylesheets,
	jade, jadetex, etc; see <filename>README.docbook</filename> for
	more information (pre-formatted versions of the documentation
	are available, and you can compile Kannel itself even without
	the documentation tools).</para></listitem>
	
	<listitem><para>GNU autoconf, if you want to modify the
	configuration script.</para></listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
	
	</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Compiling the gateway</title>

	<para>If you are using Kannel on a supported platform, or one
	that is similar enough to one, compiling Kannel is trivial.
	After you have unpacked the source package of your choosing,
	or after you have checked out the source code from CVS, enter
	the following commands:
	
<screen><userinput>./configure</userinput>
<userinput>make</userinput></screen>
	
	The <filename>configure</filename> script investigates various things on your computer for the Kannel compilation needs, and
	writes out the <filename>Makefile</filename> used to compile
	Kannel. <command>make</command> then runs the commands to
	actually compile Kannel.</para>
	
	<para>If either command writes out an error message and stops
	before it finishes its job, you have a problem, and you either
	need to fix it yourself, if you can, or report the
	problem to the Kannel project. See <xref linkend="bug-reporting">
	for details.</para>
	
	<para>For detailed instruction on using the configuration
	script, see file <filename>INSTALL</filename>.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Installing the gateway</title>

	<para>After you have compiled Kannel, you need to install
	certain programs in a suitable place. This is most easily
	done by using <command>make</command> again:
	
<screen><userinput>make bindir=<replaceable>/path/to/directory</replaceable> install</userinput></screen>

	Replace <replaceable>/path/to/directory</replaceable> with the
	pathname of the actual directory where the programs should be
	installed. The programs that are installed are (as filenames
	from the root of the source directory):
	
	<simplelist>
	<member><filename>gw/bearerbox</filename></member>
	<member><filename>gw/smsbox</filename></member>
	<member><filename>gw/wapbox</filename></member>
	</simplelist>
	
	The version number of the gateway is added to the file names
	during installation. This makes it easier to have several
	versions installed, and makes it easy to go back to an older
	version if the new version proves problematic.</para>
	
	<para>Kannel consists of three programs called boxes: the
	bearer box is the interface towards the phones. It accepts
	WAP and SMS messages from the phones and sends them to the
	other boxes. The SMS box handles SMS gateway functionality,
	and the WAP box handles WAP gateway functionality. There can
	be several SMS boxes and several WAP boxes running and they
	don't have to run on the same host. This makes it possible
	to handle much larger loads.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Using pre-compiled binary packages</title>

	<para>Pre-compiled binary packages are not yet available,
	sorry.</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>









<chapter>
<title>Using the gateway</title>

	<para>This chapter explains how the gateway core, bearerbox,
        is configured and used.
	It covers the configuration file, keeping an eye on the gateway
	while it is running, and using the HTTP interface to control
	the gateway.</para>

        <para>After this chapter there is distinct chapter for each
        kind of gateway use: WAP gateway, SMS gateway and combined
        gateway. These chapters explain the configuration and other
        aspects of gateway of that type.</para>

	<para>There is only one configuration file for all parts of
	Kannel, although when Kannel is distributed to several hosts
	some lines from the configuration file can be removed in some
	hosts.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Configuring the gateway</title>

	<para>The configuration file can be divided into three parts:
	bearerbox configurations, smsbox configurations and
	wapbox configurations. Bearerbox part has one 'core' group
	and any used SMS center groups, while wapbox part has only
	one wapbox group. In smsbox part there is one smsbox group and
	then number of sms-service and sendsms-user groups.</para>

	<para>Details of each part are in an appropriate section of this
        documentation. The 'core' group used by the bearerbox is
        explained in this chapter, while 'wapbox' part is in the next
        chapter and 'smsbox', 'smsc' (SMS center), 'sms-service' and
        'sendsms-user' groups are in the SMS Kannel chapter.</para>


<sect2>
<title>Configuration file syntax</title>

	<para>A configuration file consists of groups of configuration variables. Groups are
	separated by empty lines, and each variable is defined on its
	own line. Each group in Kannel configuration is distinguished
	with a group variable. Comments are lines that begin with a number sign
	(<literal>#</literal>) and are ignored (they don't, for example,
	separate groups of variables).</para>
	
	<para>A variable definition line has the name of the variable,
	and equals sign (<literal>=</literal>) and the value of the
	variable. The name of the variable can contain any characters
	except whitespace and equals. The value of the variable is a
	string, with or without quotation marks (<literal>"</literal>)
	around it. Quotation marks are needed if the variable needs to
	begin or end with whitespace or contain special characters. Normal C 	escape character syntax works inside quotation marks.</para>
	
	<para>Perhaps an example will make things easier to comprehend:

<programlisting>
1    # A do-nothing service.
2    group = sms-service
3    keyword = nop
4    text = "You asked nothing and I did it!"
5
6    # Default service.
4    group = sms-service
8    keyword = default
9    text = "No services defined"
</programlisting>

	The above snippet defines the keyword <literal>nop</literal>
	for an SMS service, and a default action for situation when
	the keyword in the SMS message does not match any defined
	service.</para>
	
	<para>Lines 1 and 6 are comment lines. Line 5 separates the
	two groups. The remaining lines define variables. The
	group type is defined by the group variable value.</para>
	
	<para>The various variables that are understood in each type
	of configuration group are explained below.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Core configuration</title>

  <para>Configuration for Kannel <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> always
  include a group for general bearerbox configuration. This group is
  named as 'core' in configuration file, and should be the first group
  in the configuration file.</para>

  <para>As its simplest form, 'core' group looks like this:

<programlisting>
group = core
admin-port = 13000
admin-password = f00bar
</programlisting>

   Naturally this is not sufficient for any real use, as you want to
   use Kannel as an SMS gateway, or WAP gateway, or both. Thus, one or
   more of the optional configuration variables are used.</para>


 <table frame=none>
  <title>Core Group Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=3>
  <thead>
   <row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>group</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>core</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       This is a mandatory variable
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>admin-port</literal></entry>
     <entry>port-number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        The port number in which the bearerbox listens to HTTP
        adminstration commands. It is NOT the same as the HTTP
        port of the local www server, just invent any port, but
        it must be over 1023 unless you are running Kannel as a
        root process (not recommended)
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>admin-password</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
         Password for HTTP administration commands (see below)
     </entry></row>
   
    <row><entry><literal>admin-deny-ip</literal></entry>
     <entry morerows=1>IP-list</entry>
     <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
        These lists can be used to prevent connection from given IP 
  addresses. Each list can have several addresses, separated with    
  semicolons (';'). An asterisk ('*') can be used
        as a wildcard in a place of any ONE number, so *.*.*.*
        matches any IP.
     </entry></row>
    <row><entry><literal>admin-allow-ip</literal></entry></row>


    <row><entry><literal>smsbox-port</literal></entry>
     <entry>port-number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        This is the port number to which the smsboxes, if any, connect.
        As with admin-port, this can be anything you want. Must be set
        if you want to handle any SMS traffic.
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>wapbox-port</literal></entry>
     <entry>port-number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Like smsbox-port, but for wapbox-connections. If not set,
        Kannel cannot handle WAP traffic
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>box-deny-ip</literal></entry>
     <entry morerows=1>IP-list</entry>
     <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
        These lists can be used to prevent connection from given IP 
        addresses. Each list can have several addresses, 
        separated with semicolons (';'). An asterisk ('*') can be used
        as a wildcard in place of any ONE number, so *.*.*.*
        matches any IP.
     </entry></row>
    <row><entry><literal>bow-allow-ip</literal></entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>wdp-interface-name</literal></entry>
     <entry>IP or '*'</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If this is set, Kannel listens to WAP UDP packets incoming to
        ports 9200-9208, bound to given IP. If no spesific IP is
        needed, use just an asterisk ('*'). If UDP messages are
        listened to, wapbox-port variable MUST be set.
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>log-file</literal></entry>
     <entry>filename</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        A file in which to write a log. This in addition to <literal>stdout</literal>
        and any log file defined in command line. Log-file in 'core'
        group is only used by the bearerbox.
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>log-level</literal></entry>
     <entry>number 0..5</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Minimum level of logfile events logged. 0 is for 'debug', 1
        'info', 2 'warning, 3 'error' and 4 'panic' (see Command Line
        Options)
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>access-log</literal></entry>
     <entry>filename</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        A file in which information about received/sent SMS messages 
        is stored. Access-log in 'core' group is only used by the
        bearerbox.

     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>unified-prefix</literal></entry>
     <entry>prefix-list</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        String to unify received phone numbers, for SMSC routing and
        to ensure that SMS centers can handle them properly. 
        This is applied to 'sender' number when receiving SMS
        messages from SMS Center and for 'receiver' number when
        receiving messages from SMSbox (either sendsms message or
         reply to original message). Format is that first comes the
        unified prefix, then all prefixes which are replaced by the
        unified prefix, separated with comma (','). For example,
        for Finland an unified-prefix "+358,00358,0;+,00" should do the trick. 
        If there are several unified prefixes, separate their rules with
        semicolon (';'), like "+35850,050;+35840,040". <emphasis>Note
        that prefix routing is next to useless now that there are
        SMSC ID entries</emphasis>

     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>white-list</literal></entry>
     <entry>URL</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Load a list of accepted senders of SMS messages. If a sender
        of an SMS message is not in this list, any message received
        from the SMS Center is discarded. See notes of phone number
        format from numhash.h header file. NOTE: the system has only
        a precision of last 9 or 18 digits of phone numbers, so
        beware!
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>black-list</literal></entry>
     <entry>URL</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        As white-list, but SMS messages from these numbers are
        automatically discarded
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>http-proxy-host</literal></entry>
     <entry>hostname</entry>
     <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
        Enable the use of an HTTP proxy for all HTTP requests.
     </entry></row>
    <row><entry><literal>http-proxy-port</literal></entry>
     <entry>port-number</entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>http-proxy-exceptions</literal></entry>
     <entry>URL-list</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
         A list of excluded hosts from being used via a
         proxy. Separate each entry with space.
     </entry></row>
    

  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

  <para>A sample more complex 'core' group could be something like
  this:

<programlisting>
group = core
admin-port = 13000
admin-password = f00bar
admin-deny-ip = "*.*.*.*"
admin-allow-ip = "127.0.0.1;200.100.0.*"
smsbox-port = 13003
wapbox-port = 13004
box-deny-ip = "*.*.*.*"
box-allow-ip = "127.0.0.1;200.100.0.*"
wdp-interface-name = "*"
log-file = "kannel.log"
log-level = 1
access-log = "kannel.access"
unified-prefix = "+358,00358,0;+,00"
white-list = "http://localhost/whitelist.txt"
</programlisting>
  
    </para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Running Kannel</title>

	<para>To start the gateway, you need to start each box you need.
	You always need the bearer box, and depending on whether you want
	WAP and SMS gateways you need to start the WAP and SMS boxes. If
	you want, you can run several of them, but we'll explain the
	simple case of only running one each.</para>


<sect2>
<title>Starting the gateway</title>

  <para>After you have compiled Kannel and edited configuration file
  for your taste, you can either run Kannel from command line or use
  supplied <literal>start-stop-daemon</literal> and
  <literal>run_kannel_box</literal> programs to use it as a daemon
  service (more documentation about that later).</para>

  <para>If you cannot or do not know how to set up daemon systems or
  just want to test Kannel, you probably want to start it from
  command line. This means that you probably want to have one terminal
  window for each box you want to start (xterm or screen will do
  fine). To start the bearerbox, give the following command:

<screen><userinput>./bearerbox -v 1 [conffile]</userinput></screen>

  The <option>-v 1</option> sets the logging level to
  <literal>INFO</literal>. This way, you won't see a large amount of
  debugging output (the default is <literal>DEBUG</literal>). Full
  explanation of Kannel command line arguments is below.</para>

  <para><emphasis>[conffile]</emphasis> is the name of the
  configuration file you are using with Kannel. The basic distribution
  packet comes with two sample configuration files,
  <literal>smskannel.conf</literal> and
  <literal>wapkannel.conf</literal> (in <literal>gw</literal>
  subdirectory), of which the first one is for
  testing out SMS Kannel and the second one for setting up a WAP
  Kannel. Feel free to edit those configuration files to set up your
  own specialized system.</para>

  <para>After the bearer box, you can start the WAP box:
	
<screen><userinput>./wapbox -v 1 [conffile]</userinput></screen>

  or the SMS box:

<screen><userinput>./smsbox -v 1 [conffile]</userinput></screen>

  or both, of course. The order does not matter, except that you need
  to start the bearer box before the other boxes. Without the bearer
  box, the other boxes won't even start.</para>

  <para>Please note that if you using SMS Kannel, you
  <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> start up any <literal>fakesmsc</literal>
  systems before starting the bearerbox, if there are any
  <literal>fake</literal> SMSC groups in configuration file, like
  there is one in supplied <literal>smskannel.conf</literal>.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="arguments">
<title id="arguments.title">Command line options</title>

 <para>Bearerbox, smsbox and wapbox each accept certain command line options
   and arguments when they are launched. These arguments are:</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>Kannel Command Line Options</title>
  <tgroup cols=2>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>-v &lt;level&gt;</literal></entry>
        <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
             Set verbosity level for stdout (screen) logging. Default is 0,
             which means 'debug'. 1 is 'info, 2 'warning', 3
             'error' and 4 'panic'
        </entry></row>
   <row><entry><literal>--verbosity &lt;level&gt;</literal></entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>-D &lt;places&gt;</literal></entry>
        <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
             Set debug-places for 'debug' level output. 
        </entry></row>
   <row><entry><literal>--debug &lt;places&gt;</literal></entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>-F &lt;file-name&gt;</literal></entry>
        <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
              Log to file named file-name, too. Does not overrun or
              affect any logfile defined in configuration file.
        </entry></row>
   <row><entry><literal>--logfile &lt;file-name&gt;</literal></entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>-V &lt;level&gt;</literal></entry>
        <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
            Set verbosity level for that extra logfile (default 0,
            which means 'debug'). Does not affect verbosity level of
            the logfile defined in configuration file, not verbosity
            level of the <literal>stdout</literal> output.
        </entry></row>
   <row><entry><literal>--fileverbosity &lt;level&gt;</literal></entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>-S</literal></entry>
        <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
             Start the system initially at SUSPENDED state (see below,
              bearerbox only)
        </entry></row>
   <row><entry><literal>--suspended</literal></entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>-I</literal></entry>
        <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
             Start the system initially at ISOLATED state (see below,
              bearerbox only)
        </entry></row>
   <row><entry><literal>--isolated</literal></entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>-H</literal></entry>
        <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
             Only try to open HTTP sendsms interface; if it
             fails, only warn about that, do not exit. (smsbox only)
        </entry></row>
   <row><entry><literal>--tryhttp</literal></entry></row>

 </tbody>
 </tgroup>
 </table>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Kannel statuses</title>

    <para>In Kannel, there are four states for the program (which
    currently directly only apply to bearerbox):</para>
 
    <orderedlist numeration=loweralpha>
     <listitem><para>
       Running. The gateway accepts, proceeds and relies 
       messages normally. This is the default state for the bearerbox.
     </para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>
 Suspended. The gateway does not accept any new messages from SMS
   centers nor from UDP ports. Neither does ir accept new sms and wapbox
   connections nor sends any messages already in the system
   onward.

     </para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>
 Isolated. In this state, the gateway does not accept any messages
   from external message providers, which means SMS Centers and UDP
   ports. It still processes any messages in the system and can
   accept new messages from sendsms interface in smsbox.

     </para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>

   Shutdown. When the gateway is brought down, it does not accept any
   new messages from SMS centers and UDP ports, but processes all
   systems already in the system. As soon as any queues are emptied,
   the system exits

   </para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
 
  <para>
The state can be changed via HTTP administration interface (see below),
and shutdown can also be initiated via TERM or INT signal from
terminal. In addition, the bearerbox can be started already in
suspended or isolated state with -S or -I command line option, see
above.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>HTTP administration</title>

<para>Kannel can be controlled via an HTTP administration interface. All
commands are done as normal HTTP queries, so they can be easily done
from command line like this:

<screen><userinput>% lynx -dump "http://localhost:12345/cgi-bin/shutdown?password=bar"</userinput></screen>

...in which the '12345' is the configured admin-port in Kannel
configuration file (see above). For most commands, admin-password is required as a
cgi-bin argument as shown above. In addition, HTTP administration can
be denied from certain IP addresses, as explained in configuration
chapter.</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>Kannel HTTP Administration Commands</title>
  <tgroup cols=2>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>status</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Get the current status of the gateway. Tells the current state
        (see above) and total number of messages relied and queuing in
        the system right now. Also lists the total number of smsbox
        and wapbox connections.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>suspend</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Set Kannel state as 'suspended' (see above). Password
        required.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>isolate</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Set Kannel state as 'isolated' (see above). Password required.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>resume</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Set Kannel state as 'running' if it is suspended or isolated.
        Password required.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>shutdown</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Bring down the gateway, by setting state to 'shutdown'. After
        a shutdown is initiated, there is no other chance to resume
        normal operation. However, 'status' command still works.
        Password required. If shutdown is sent for a second time, the
        gateway is forced down, even if it has still messages in
        queue.
   </entry></row>
  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

</sect2>
  
</sect1>
</chapter>






<chapter id="wap-gateway">
<title>Setting up a WAP gateway</title>

    <para>This chapter tells you how to set Kannel up as a WAP
    gateway.</para>

<sect1>
<title>WAP gateway configuration</title>

  <para>To set up a WAP Kannel, you have to edit the 'core' group in the
  configuration file, and define the 'wapbox' group.</para>

  <para>You must set following variables for the 'core' group:  
    <literal>wapbox-port</literal> and
    <literal>wdp-interface-name</literal>. See previous chapter about
    details of these variables.</para>

  <para>With standard distribution, a sample configuration file
  <literal>wapkannel.conf</literal> is supplied. You may want to take
  a look at that when setting up a WAP Kannel.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Wapbox configuration</title>

  <para>If you have set <literal>wapbox-port</literal> variable in the
  'core' configuration group, you <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> supply
  a 'wapbox' group.</para>

  <para>The simplest working 'wapbox' group looks like this:
<programlisting>
group = wapbox
bearerbox-host = localhost
</programlisting>

   There is, however, multiple optional variables for the 'wapbox'
   group.</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>Wapbox Group Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=3>
  <thead>
   <row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>group</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>wapbox</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       This is mandatory variable
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>bearerbox-host</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>hostname</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        The machine in which the bearerbox is. 
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>timer-freq</literal></entry>
     <entry>value-in-seconds</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
         The frequency of how often timers are checked out. Default is 1 
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>map-url</literal></entry>
     <entry>URL-pair</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        The pair is separated with space.
        Adds a single mapping for the left side URL to the given destination.
        If you append an asterisk `*' to the left side URL, its prefix
        Is matched against the incoming URL. Whenever the prefix matches,
        the URL will be replaced completely by the right side. In addition, if 	  if you append an asterisk to the right side URL, the part
        of the incoming URL coming after the prefix, will be appended
        to the right side URL. Thus, for a line:
                map-url = "http://source/* http://destination/*"
        and an incoming URL of "http://source/some/path", the result
        will be "http://destination/some/path"
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>map-url-max</literal></entry>
     <entry>number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If you need more than one mapping, set this to the highest number
        mapping you need. The default gives you 10 mappings, numbered
        from 0 to 9. Default: 9
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>map-url-0</literal></entry>
     <entry>URL-pair</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Adds a mapping for the left side URL to the given destination URL.
        Repeat these lines, with 0 replaced by a number up to map-url-max,
        if you need several mappings.
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>device-home</literal></entry>
     <entry>URL</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Adds a mapping for the URL DEVICE:home (as sent by Phone.com browsers)
        to the given destination URL. There is no default mapping.
        NOTE: the mapping is added with both asterisks, as described above
        for the "map-url" setting. Thus, the above example line is
        equivalent to writing
                map-url = "DEVICE:home* http://some.where/*"

     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>log-file</literal></entry>
     <entry>filename</entry>
     <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
       As with bearerbox 'core' group. 
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>log-level</literal></entry>
     <entry>number 0..5</entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>syslog-level</literal></entry>
     <entry>number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
         <emphasis>Somebody needs to explain this a bit...</emphasis>
     </entry></row>


  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>


<programlisting>
</programlisting>
</sect2>
  
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Running WAP gateway</title>

 <para>WAP Gateway is ran as explained in previous chapter.</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>










<chapter id="sms-gateway">
<title>Setting up a SMS Gateway</title>

    <para>This chapter is a more detailed guide on how to set up Kannel as an
    SMS gateway.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Required components</title>

    <para>To set up an SMS gateway, you need, in addition to machine
    running Kannel, an access to (operator's) SMS center, or possibly
    to multiple ones. The list of supported SMS centers and their
    configuration variables is below.</para>

    <para>If you do not have such an access, you can still
    use Kannel as an SMS gateway via <emphasis>phone-as-SMSC</emphasis> 
    feature, by using a GSM phone as virtual SMS center.</para>

    <para>In addition to SMS center (real or virtual), you need some
    server to handle any SMS requests received. This server then has
    simple or more complex cgi-bins, programs or scripts to serve HTTP
    requests generated by Kannel in response to received SMS
    messages. These services can also initiate SMS push via Kannel
    smsbox HTTP sendsms interface.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>SMS gateway configuration</title>

  <para>To set up a SMS Kannel, you have to edit the 'core' group in the
  configuration file, and define an 'smsbox' group plus one or more
  'sms-service' groups, plus possibly one or more 'sendsms-user' groups.</para>

  <para>For the 'core' group, you must set the following variable:  
    <literal>smsbox-port</literal>. In addition, you may be interested
    to set <literal>unified-prefix</literal>,
    <literal>white-list</literal> and/or <literal>black-list</literal>
    variables. See above for details of these variables.</para>

  <para> A sample configuration file <literal>smskannel.conf</literal> is supplied with the standard distribution. You may want to take
  a look at that when setting up an SMS Kannel.</para>

<sect2>
<title>SMS centers</title>

    <para>To set up the SMS center at Kannel, you have to add a 'smsc'
    group into configuration file. 
    This group must include all the data needed to connect
    that SMS center. You may also want to define an ID
    (identification) name for the SMSC, for logging and routing
    purposes.</para>

    <para>SMSC ID is an abstract name for the connection. It can be
    anything you like, but you should avoid any special
    characters. You do not need to use ID, but rely on SMS center IP
    address and other information. However, if you use the ID, you do
    not need to re-define sms-services nor routing systems if the IP
    of the SMS Center is changed, for example.</para>

    <para>Common 'smsc' group variables are defined in the following
    table. The first two (<literal>group</literal> and
    <literal>smsc</literal>) are mandatory, but rest can be used if
    needed.</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>SMSC Group Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=3>
  <thead>
   <row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>group</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>smsc</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       This is a mandatory variable
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>smsc</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Identifies the SMS center type. See below
       for a complete list.
     </entry></row>


   <row><entry><literal>smsc-id</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        An optional name or id for the smsc. Any string is
        acceptable, but semicolon ';' may cause problems, so avoid
        it and any other special non-alphabet characters. 
        This 'id' is written into log files and can be used to
        route SMS messages, and to specify the used SMS-service. 
        Several smsc'es can have the same id. The name is case-insensitive.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>denied-smsc-id</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>id-list</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        SMS messages with SMSC ID equal to any of the IDs in this list
        are never routed to this SMSC. Multiple entries are separated 
        with semicolons (';')

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>preferred-smsc-id</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>id-list</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        SMS messages with SMSC ID from this list are sent to this SMSC
        instead than to SMSC without that ID as preferred. Multiple
        entries are separated with semicolons (';')
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>denied-prefix</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>prefix-list</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        A list of phone number prefixes which are NOT accepted to be
        sent through this SMSC. Multiple entries are separated with 
        semicolon (';'). For example, "040;050" prevents sending of
        any SMS message with prefix of 040 or 050 through this SMSC
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>preferred-prefix</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>prefix-list</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        As <literal>denied-prefix</literal>, but SMS messages with receiver starting
        with any of these prefixes is prefereably sent through this
        SMSC. In a case of multiple preferences, one is selected at random
        (also if there are preferences, SMSC is selected randomly)

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>alt-charset</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>number</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        As some SMS Centers do not follow the standards in character
        coding, an <literal>alt-charset</literal> kludge is
        presented. Currently implemented
        alternative charsets are defined in "alt_charsets.h" and new ones
        can be added to appropriate smsc-code.
     </entry></row>

  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

   <para>In addition to these common variables there are several
   variables used by certain SMS center connections. Each currently
   supported SMS center type is explained below, with configuration
   group for each. Note that many of them use variables with same
   name, but most also have some specific variables.</para>

   <para><emphasis>NOTE: SMS center configuration variables are a bit 
   incomplete, and will be updated as soon as people responsible for
   the protocols are contacted. Meanwhile, please have
   patience.</emphasis></para>


<sect3>
<title>Nokia CIMD 1.37 and 2.0</title>

<programlisting>
group = smsc
smsc = cimd
host = 100.101.102.103
port = 600
smsc-username = foo
smsc-password = bar

group = smsc
smsc = cimd2
host = 100.101.102.103
port = 600
smsc-username = foo
smsc-password = bar
keepalive = 5 
</programlisting>

 <informaltable frame=none>
  <tgroup cols=3><thead><row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row></thead><tbody>

   <row><entry><literal>host</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>hostname</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Machine that runs the SMSC. As IP (100.100.100.100) 
        or hostname (their.machine.here)
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>port</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>port-number</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Port number in the smsc host machine
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>smsc-username</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Username in the SMSC machine/connection account
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>smsc-password</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Password in the SMSC machine needed to contact SMSC
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>keepalive</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>number</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       SMSC connection will not be left idle for longer than this many
       minutes.  The right value to use depends on how eager the SMSC
       is to close idle connections.  5 minutes is a good guess.  If you
       see many unexplained reconnects, try lowering this value.
       Set it to 0 to disable this feature.
     </entry></row>

   </tbody></tgroup></informaltable>
   
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>CMG UCP/EMI 2.0</title>

  <para>Kannel supports two types of connections with CMG SMS centers:
  direct TCP/IP connections (<literal>emi_ip</literal>) and
  ISDN/modem connection (<literal>emi</literal>). Sample
  configurations for these are:</para>
  
<programlisting>
group = smsc
smsc = emi_ip
host = 103.102.101.100
port = 600
smsc-username = foo
smsc-password = bar
our-port = 600 (optional bind in our end)
receive-port = 700 (the port in which the SMSC will contact)

group = smsc
smsc = emi
host = 100.102.100.102
phone = ...
device = /dev/tty0
smsc-username = foo
smsc-password = bar
</programlisting>

 <informaltable frame=none>
  <tgroup cols=3><thead><row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row></thead><tbody>

   <row><entry><literal>host</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>hostname</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Machine that runs SMSC. As IP (100.100.100.100) 
        or hostname (their.machine.here)
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>port</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>port-number</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Port number in the SMSC host machine
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>device</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>device-name</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
          The device the modem is connected to, like <literal>/dev/ttyS0</literal>.
          ISDN connection only.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>our-port</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>port-number</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Optional port number in which to bind the connection in our
     end. TCP/IP connection only.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>receive-port</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>port-number</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        The port number we have to listen to and to which the SMS center
        connects when it has messages to send. TCP/IP
        connection only.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>connect-allow-ip</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>IP-list</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       If set, only connections from these IP addresses are accepted
       to receiver-port. TCP/IP connection only.
     </entry></row>

   </tbody></tgroup></informaltable>
   

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>SMPP 3.3</title>

   <para>This implements Short Message Peer to Peer (SMPP) Protocol
   3.3</para>

<programlisting>
group = smsc
smsc = smpp
host = 127.0.0.1
port = 600
receive-port = 700      (optional, receiver port if it a different one)
system-id = "param, ask from dealer.. 'same' as username"
smsc-password = foo
system-type = "param, ask from dealer"
address-range = "" (regex of received numbers)
</programlisting>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Sema Group SMS2000 OIS 4.0 and 5.0</title>
 
   <para>The 4.0 implementation is over Radio PAD (X.28). Following
   configuration variables are needed, and if you find out the more
   exact meaning, please send a report.</para>

   <para>The 5.0 implementation uses X.25 access gateway.</para>
  
<programlisting>
group = smsc
smsc = sema
device = /dev/tty0
smsc_nua = (X121 smsc address)
 #       The address of an SMSC for Sema SMS2000 protocols using an X.28 
 #       connection.
home_nua = (x121 radio pad address)
 #       The address of a radio PAD implementing Sema SMS2000 using X.28 
 #       connection.
 #
wait_report = 0/1 (0 means false, 1 means true)
 #       Report indicator used by the Sema SMS2000 protocol. Optional.

group = smsc
smsc = ois
host = 103.102.101.100
port = 10000
receive-port = 10000 (the port in which the SMSC will contact)
ois-debug-level = number 0 to 8  (extra debug, optional, see smsc_ois.c)
</programlisting>

</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>GSM modem</title>

   <para>Kannel can use a GSM modem as an SMS center.</para>

<programlisting>
group = smsc
smsc = at
modemtype = wavecom
device = /dev/ttyS0
pin = 2345
</programlisting>

 <informaltable frame=none>
  <tgroup cols=3><thead><row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row></thead><tbody>

   <row><entry><literal>modemtype</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Modems from different manufacturers have slightly different
        behaviour. We need to know what type of modem is used.
        Supported types are: <literal>wavecom</literal>, 
        <literal>premicell</literal>, <literal>siemens</literal>.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>device</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>device-name</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
          The device the modem is connected to, like <literal>/dev/ttyS0</literal>.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>pin</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
         This is the PIN number of the SIM card in the GSM modem. You can specify
         this option if your SIM has never been used before and needs to have
         the PIN number entered. The PIN is usually a four digit number.
     </entry></row>

   </tbody></tgroup></informaltable>

</sect3>


<sect3>
<title>Fake SMSC</title>

  <para>Fake SMSC is a simple protocol to test out Kannel. It is not
  a real SMS center, and cannot be used to send or receive SMS
  messages from real phones. So, it is ONLY used for testing purposes.
  </para>

  <para>Please note that if you use one or more fake SMSCs, you must
  start them before starting the bearerbox.</para>

<programlisting>
group = smsc
smsc = fake
host = localhost
port = 10000
</programlisting>

 <informaltable frame=none>
  <tgroup cols=3><thead><row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row></thead><tbody>

   <row><entry><literal>host</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>hostname</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Machine that runs the SMSC. As IP (100.100.100.100) 
        or hostname (their.machine.here)
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>port</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>port-number</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Port number in smsc host machine
     </entry></row>

   </tbody></tgroup></informaltable>

</sect3>


<sect3>
<title>Using multiple SMS centers</title>

    <para>If you have several SMS center connections (multiple
    operators or a number of GSM modems) you need to configure one smsc
    group per SMS center (or GSM modem). When doing this, you might
    want to use routing systems to rout messages to specific centers -
    for example, you have 2 operator SMS centers, and the other is
    much faster and cheaper to use.</para>

    <para>To set up routing systems, first give an unique ID for each
    SMS center - or if you want to treat multiple ones completely
    identical, give them identical ID. Then use 
    <literal>preferred-smsc-id</literal> and
    <literal>denied-smsc-id</literal> to set up the routing to your
    taste. See also SMS PUSH settings ('sendsms-user' groups), below.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Smsbox configuration</title>

  <para>You must define an 'smsbox' group into the configuration file to be
  able to use SMS Kannel. The simplest working 'smsbox' group looks 
   like this:

<programlisting>
group = smsbox
bearerbox-host = localhost
</programlisting>

   ...but you would most probably want to define 'sendsms-port' to be
   able to use SMS push.</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>Smsbox Group Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=3>
  <thead>
   <row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>group</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>smsbox</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       This is a mandatory variable
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>bearerbox-host</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>hostname</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        The machine in which the bearerbox is. 
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>sendsms-port</literal></entry>
     <entry>port-number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        The port in which any sendsms HTTP requests are done. As with
        other ports in Kannel, can be set as anything desired.
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>sendsms-chars</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Only these characters are allowed in 'to' field when send-SMS
        service is requested via HTTP. Naturally, you should allow 
        at least <literal>0123456789</literal>. The
        <emphasis>space</emphasis> character (' ') has special
        meaning: it is used to separate multiple phone numbers from
        each other in multi-send. To disable this feature, do not have
        it as an accepted character. If this variable is
        not set, the default set <literal>"0123456789&nbsp;+-"</literal> is used.
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>global-sender</literal></entry>
     <entry>phone-number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If set, all sendsms originators are set as these before
        proceeding. Note that in a case of most SMS centers you
        cannot set the sender number, but it is automatically set
        as the number of SMSC
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>log-file</literal></entry>
     <entry>filename</entry>
     <entry morerows=2 valign=bottom>
       As with the bearerbox 'core' group. Access-log is used to store
       information about MO and send-sms requests. Can be named same as the 
       'main' access-log (in 'core' group).
     </entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>log-level</literal></entry>
     <entry>number 0..5</entry></row>

    <row><entry><literal>access-log</literal></entry>
     <entry>filename</entry></row>

  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

   <para>A typical 'smsbox' group could be something like this:

<programlisting>
group = smsbox
bearerbox-host = localhost
sendsms-port = 13131
sendsms-chars = "0123456789 "
global-sender = 123456
access-log = "kannel.access"
log-file = "smsbox.log"
log-level = 0
</programlisting>
 </para>


</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>SMS-service configurations</title>

    <para>Now that you have an SMS center connection to send and
    receive SMS messages you need to define services for incoming
    messages. This is done via 'sms-service' configuration
    groups.</para>

    <para>These groups define SMS services in the smsbox, so they are only
    used by the smsbox. Each service is recognized from the first word
    in an SMS message.  By adding a username and password in the URL
    in the following manner
    "http://luser:password@host.domain:port/path?query" we can perform
    HTTP Basic authentication.</para>

    <para>The simplest service group looks like this:

<programlisting>
group = sms-service
keyword = www
url = "http://%S"
</programlisting>
     
     This service grabs any SMS with 'www' as the first word, and then
     does an HTTP request to an URL which is taken from the rest of the
     message. Any result is sent back to the phone (or requester), but is
     truncated to 160 characters, naturally.</para>

     <para>Service group <literal>default</literal> has a special
     meaning: if the incoming message is not routed to any other
     service, <literal>default</literal> 'sms-service' group is used.
     You should always define <literal>default</literal> service.</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>SMS-Service Group Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=3>
  <thead>
   <row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>group</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>sms-service</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       This is a mandatory variable
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>keyword</literal></entry>
     <entry>word</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Services are identified by the first word in the SMS Each
        `%s' in the URL corresponds to one word in the SMS message.
         Words are separated with spaces. A keyword is matched only if
         the number of words in the SMS message is the same as the
         number of `%s' fields in the URL. This allows you to
        configure the gateway to use different URLs for the same
        keyword depending on the number of words the SMS message
        contains.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>aliases</literal></entry>
     <entry>word-list</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If the service has aliases, they are listed as a list with 
        each entry separated with a semicolon (';')

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>url</literal></entry>
     <entry>URL</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Requested URL. The url can include a list of parameters, which are
        parsed before the url is fetched. See below for these
        parameters.


     </entry></row>


   <row><entry><literal>file</literal></entry>
     <entry>filename</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        File read from a local disc. Use this variable only if no
        <literal>url</literal> is set. All escape codes (parameters)
        in <literal>url</literal> are supported in filename. 
        The last character of the file (usually linefeed) is removed.

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>text</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Predefined text answer. Only if there is neither <literal>url</literal> nor 
        <literal>file</literal> set. Escape codes (parameters) are
        usable here, too.

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>accepted-smsc</literal></entry>
     <entry>id-list</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Accept ONLY SMS messages arriving from SMSC with matching ID.
        Separate multiple entries with ';'. For example, if 
         <literal>accepted-smsc</literal>
        is "RL;SON", accept messages which originate from SMSC with
        ID set as 'RL' or 'SON'

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>faked-sender</literal></entry>
     <entry>phone-number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        This number is set as sender. Most SMS centers ignore this,
        and use their fixed number instead. This option
        overrides all other sender setting methods.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>max-messages</literal></entry>
     <entry>number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        The total maximum of SMSes in reply. Default is 1. If
        <literal>max-messages</literal> is set to 0, no reply is sent, 
        except for error messages. 
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>concetenation</literal></entry>
     <entry>0 or 1</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
         If set to 1 enables the concatenation of SMS's for long
         messages (otherwise they are send as just multiple SMSes)
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>split-chars</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Allowed characters to split the message into several messages.
        So, with "#!" the message is split from last '#' or '!', which is 
        included in the previous part

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>split-suffix</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If the message is split into several ones, this string is appended to 
        each message except the last one
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>omit-empty</literal></entry>
     <entry>0 or 1</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If set to other than '0', 'no data' messages are not sent to receiver
        in case of an empty reply from the service provider.

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>header</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If specified, this string is automatically added to each SMS sent with
        this service. If the message is split, it is added to each part

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>footer</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        As header, but not inserted into head but appended to end

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>prefix</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
        Stuff in answer that is cut away, only things between prefix
        and suffix is left. In-casesensitive. Matches the first prefix
        and then the first suffix.

     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>suffix</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry></row>

  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>






 <table frame=none>
  <title>Parameters (Escape Codes)</title>
  <tgroup cols=2>
  <tbody>

<row><entry><literal>%s</literal></entry><entry>
next word from the SMS message, starting with
                         the second one (i.e., the first word, the
                         keyword, is not included); problematic characters
                         for URLs are encoded (e.g., '+' becomes '%2B')
                 
</entry></row>

<row><entry><literal>%S</literal></entry><entry>
same as %s, but '*' is converted to '~' (useful
                         when user enters a URL) and URL encoding isn't done
                         (all others do URL encode)
</entry></row>

<row><entry><literal>%r</literal></entry><entry>
words not yet used by %s; e.g., if the message
                         is "FOO BAR FOOBAR BAZ", and the has been one %s,
                         %r will mean "FOOBAR BAZ"
</entry></row>

<row><entry><literal>%a</literal></entry><entry>
all words of the SMS message, including the first one
</entry></row>

<row><entry><literal>%t</literal></entry><entry>
the time the message was sent, formatted as
                         "YYYY-MM-DD HH:MM", e.g., "1999-09-21 14:18"
</entry></row>

<row><entry><literal>%p</literal></entry><entry>
the phone number of the sender of the SMS message
</entry></row>

<row><entry><literal>%P</literal></entry><entry>
the phone number of the receiver of the SMS message
</entry></row>

<row><entry><literal>%q</literal></entry><entry>
like %p, but a leading `00' is replaced with `+'
</entry></row>

<row><entry><literal>%Q</literal></entry><entry>
like %P, but a leading `00' is replaced with `+'
</entry></row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>



 <para>Some sample 'sms-service' groups:

<programlisting>
group = sms-service
keyword = nop
text = "You asked nothing and I did it!"

group = sms-service
keyword = complex
url = "http://my.applet.machine/Servlet/kludge2?sender=%p&amp;text=%r"
max-messages = 3
header = "<<<"
footer = ">>>"

group = sms-service
keyword = default
text = "No action spesified"
</programlisting>
</para>


</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>SendSMS-user configurations</title>

   <para>To enable an SMS push, you must set
   <literal>sendsms-port</literal> into the 'smsbox' group and define one or
   more 'sendsms-user' groups. Each of these groups define one
   account, which can be used for the SMS push, via HTTP interface (see
   below)</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>SendSMS-User Group Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=3>
  <thead>
   <row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>group</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>sendsms-user</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       This is a mandatory variable
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>username</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Name for the user/account. 
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>password</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Password for the user (see HTTP interface, below)
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>user-deny-ip</literal></entry>
     <entry>IP-list</entry>
     <entry morerows=1 valign=bottom>
        As other deny/allow IP lists, but for this user (i.e. this
         user is not allowed to do the SMS push HTTP request from
         other IPs than allowed ones). If not set, there is no
         limitations.
     </entry></row>
   <row><entry><literal>user-allow-IP</literal></entry>
     <entry>IP-list</entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>forced-smsc</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
         Force SMSC ID as a 'string' (linked to SMS routing, see 'smsc' groups)
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>default-smsc</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If no SMSC ID is given with the send-sms request (see below), use
        this one. No idea to use with forced-smsc.
     </entry></row>


   <row><entry><literal>faked-sender</literal></entry>
     <entry>phone-number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        As in 'sms-service' groups
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>max-messages</literal></entry>
     <entry>number</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        If the message to be sent is longer than maximum length of an SMS
        it will be split into several parts. <literal>max-messages</literal>
        lets you specify a maximum number of individual SMS messages that
        can be used.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>concatenation</literal></entry>
     <entry>0 or 1</entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
        Long messages can be sent as independant SMS messages with
        <literal>concatenation = 0</literal> or as concatenated messages
        with <literal>concatenation = 1</literal>. Concatenated messages
        are reassembled into one long message by the receiving device.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>split-chars</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>split-suffix</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>omit-empty</literal></entry>
     <entry>0 or 1</entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>header</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>footer</literal></entry>
     <entry>string</entry></row>

  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

  <para>Some sample 'sendsms-user' groups:

<programlisting>
group = sendsms-user
username = simple
password = elpmis

group = sendsms-user
username = complex
password = 76ftY
user-deny-ip = "*.*.*.*"
user-allow-ip = "123.234.123.234"
max-messages = 3
concatenation = 1
forced-smsc = SOL
</programlisting>

   The second one is very limited and only allows a user from IP
   "123.234.123.234". On the other hand, the user can send a longer
   message, up to 3 SMSes long, which is sent as concatenated
   SMS.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Over-The-Air configurations</title>

   <para>To enable Over-The-Air configuration of phones or other client
   devices that support the protocol you need to configure a
   <literal>ota-config</literal> group and a <literal>sendsms-user</literal>.
   </para>
   
 <table frame=none>
  <title>OTA Config Group Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=3>
  <thead>
   <row>
     <entry>Variable</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>group</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>otaconfig</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       This is a mandatory variable
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>location</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>URL</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       The address of the server for your WAP services. http://your.wap.site
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>service</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Description of the service
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>ipaddress</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>IP</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
      IP address of your server 
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>phonenumber</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>phone-number</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Phone number used to establish the PPP connection
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>bearer</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Connection type: cont or temp. Defaults to cont.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>pppsecurity</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>on or off</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Enable CHAP authentication if set to on, PAP otherwise
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>authentication</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       normal or secure. Defaults to normal.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>login</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal>string</literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Login name.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>secret</literal></entry>
     <entry><literal></literal></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Login password
     </entry></row>

  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

  <para>A sample 'otaconfig' group:

<programlisting>
group = otaconfig
location = http://wap.company.com
service = "Our company's WAP site"
ipaddress = 10.11.12.13
phonenumber = 013456789
bearer = data
calltype = analog
connection = cont
pppsecurity = off
authentication = normal
login = wapusr
secret = thepasswd
</programlisting>

And a 'sendsms-user' to use with it. With concatenation enabled:

<programlisting>
group = sendsms-user
username = otauser
password = foo
max-messages = 2
concatenation = 1
</programlisting>

  </para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Setting up more complex services</title>

    <para>The basic service system is very limited - it can only
    answer to original requester and it cannot send UDH data, for
    example. This chapter explains some more sophicated and complex
    SMS service setups.</para>

<sect3>
<title>Redirected replies</title>

    <para>The basic service system always sends the answer back to
    original requester, but sometimes the content server needs to send
    something to other terminals or delay the answer. To create 
    such systems, an SMS push is used.</para>

    <para>The idea is to get the initial request, but then send no
    reply. Instead, the reply (if any) is sent via HTTP
    sendsms-interface as SMS Push. This way the service
    application has full control of the return content, and can do all
    needed formatting beforehand.</para>

    <para>Note that when no reply is wanted, remember to set the variable
    <literal>max-messages</literal> to zero (0) so that no reply is sent, unless an
    error occurs. Simple sample:</para>

<programlisting>
group = sms-service
keyword = talk
url = "http://my.applet.machine/Servlet/talk?sender=%p&amp;text=%r"
max-messages = 0
</programlisting>


</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Setting up operator specific services</title>

   <para>Those running Kannel with several SMS centers might need to
   define services according to the relying SMS center. To achieve this,
   first you need to give an ID name for SMS center connections (see
   above). Then use the <literal>accepted-smsc</literal> variable to 
   define which messages can use that service.</para>

<programlisting>
group = sms-service
keyword = weather
accepted-smsc = SOL
url = "http://my.applet.machine/Servlet/weather?sender=%p&amp;operator=SOL&amp;text=%r"
</programlisting>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Setting up multi-operator Kannel</title>

   <para>Sometimes there is a need for Kannel to listen to two (or
   more) distinct SMS centers, and messages must be routed to services
   according to wherefrom they came, and replies likewise must return
   to same SMSC. This is done via <literal>smsc-id</literal>
   magics. Here is a shortened sample configuration, which handles to
   distinct SMS servers and services:</para>

<programlisting>
group = smsc
smsc-id = A
denied-smsc-id = B
...

group = smsc
smsc-id = B
denied-smsc-id = A
...

group = sms-service
accepted-smsc = A
url = "..."

group = sms-service
accepted-smsc = B
url = "..."
</programlisting>
 
    <para>As can be seen, the <literal>smsc-id</literal> is used to
    identify the SMS center wherefrom the message came from. Then, the
    <literal>denied-smsc-id</literal> variable is used to prevent
    messages originally from the other SMS center from being sent
    through the other one. Finally 'sms-service' groups are defined
    with <literal>accepted-smsc</literal> so that they only accept
    messages from certain SMS center.</para>

    <para>If you want to use SMS push services, requesters 
    should then set the <literal>smsc</literal> request parameter, or
    'sendsms-user' groups should be defined like this:</para>

<programlisting>
group = sendsms-user
username = operator_A
password = foo
forced-smsc = A

group = sendsms-user
username = operator_B
password = bar
forced-smsc = B
</programlisting>

    <para>Note that if your SMS centers do not set the sender phone
    number but rely on number transmitted, you should set
    <literal>forced-number</literal> to all 'sendsms-user'
    groups.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Running SMS gateway</title>

 <para>WAP Gateway is ran as explained earlier. Please note
  that if you are running Kannel with <literal>fakesmsc</literal> SMS
  center configurations, you <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> launch them
  before starting up the bearerbox. Otherwise you will get 'cannot
  connect' error and bearerbox will simply exit.</para>



<sect2>
<title>Using the HTTP interface to send SMS messages</title>

	<para>After you have configured Kannel to allow the sendsms
	service, you can send SMS messages via HTTP, e.g., using a
	WWW browser. The URL looks something like this:
	
<programlisting>
http://smsbox.host.name:13013/cgi-bin/sendsms?username=foo&amp;password=bar&amp;to=0123456&amp;text=Hello+world
</programlisting>

         Thus, technically,
	you make an HTTP GET request. This means that all the information
	is stuffed into the URL. If you want to use this often via a
	browser, you probably want to make an HTML form for this.</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>SMS Push (send-sms) CGI Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=2>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>username</literal> (or <literal>user</literal>)</entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Username or account name. Must be <literal>username</literal> of the one
        'sendsms-user' group in the Kannel configuration,
        or results in 'Authorization failed' reply.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>password</literal> (or <literal>pass</literal>)</entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
       Password associated with given <literal>username</literal>. Must match
 corresponding field in the 'sendsms-user' group of
the Kannel configuration, or 'Authorization failed' is returned.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>from</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Phone number of the sender. This field is usually overridden
        by the SMS Center, or it can be overridden by
        <literal>faked-sender</literal> variable in the
        <literal>sendsms-user</literal> group. If this variable is not
        set, smsbox <literal>global-sender</literal> is used.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>to</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Phone number of the receiver. To send to multiple receivers,
   separate each entry with <emphasis>space</emphasis> (' ', '+'
   url-encoded) - but note that this can be deactivated via
   <literal>sendsms-chars</literal> in the 'smsbox' group.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>text</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Contents of the message, URL encoded as necessary. The content
        can be more than 160 characters, but then
        <literal>sendsms-user</literal> group must have
        <literal>max-messages</literal> set more than 1.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>udh</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
         Optional User Data Header (UDH) part of the message. Must be
         URL encoded.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>smsc</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Optional guideline of which SMS Center is used to send the
        message (see above). This variable can be overridden with a
        <literal>forced-smsc</literal> configuration
        variable. Likewise, the <literal>default-smsc</literal> variable
        can be used to set the SMSC if it is not set otherwise.
   </entry></row>

  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

	
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Using the HTTP interface to send OTA configuration messages</title>

       <para>OTA messages can be sent to mobile phones or devices to auto-configure the   
       settings for WAP. They are actually complex SMS messages with UDH and sent as
       concatenated messages if too long. An example URL is like this:	

<programlisting>
http://smsbox.host.name:13013/cgi-bin/sendota?username=foo&amp;password=bar&amp;phonenumber=0123456
</programlisting>
       </para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>OTA CGI Variables</title>
  <tgroup cols=2>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>username</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
        Username of the 'sendsms-user' group in Kannel configuration, that has
        been configured to send OTA messages.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>password</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
       Password associated to given <literal>username</literal>. Must match
       corresponding field in 'sendsms-user' group in Kannel configuration, or
       'Authorization failed' is returned.
   </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>phonenumber</literal></entry>
   <entry valign=bottom>
       Number of the phone that is to receive the OTA configuration message.
   </entry></row>
  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>




<chapter id="smswap-gateway">
<title>Setting up a SMS&amp;WAP gateway</title>

    <para>This chapter tells you how to set Kannel up as a combined WAP
    and SMS gateway.</para>

<sect1>
<title>SMS&amp;WAP gateway configuration</title>

   <para>Configuration is done as explained in previous chapters, you
   simply have to include all the data from both chapters into the
   configuration file.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Running SMS&amp;WAP gateway</title>

   <para>There are no special tricks to this, just launch both the smsbox
   and the wapbox in addition to the bearerbox, using multiple hosts if
   needed.</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>




<chapter id="bug-reporting">
<title>Getting help and reporting bugs</title>

	<para>This chapter explains where to find help with problems
	related to the gateway, and the preferred procedure for reporting
	bugs and sending corrections to them.</para>
	
	<para>The Kannel development mailing list is devel@kannel.org.  To subscribe, send mail to <ulink url="mailto:devel-subscribe@kannel.org">devel-subscribe@kannel.org</ulink>.
	This is currently the best location for asking help and reporting
	bugs. Please include configuration file and version number.</para>
	
</chapter>

<appendix>
<title>Using the fake WAP sender</title>

	<para>This appendix explains how to use the fake WAP sender
	to test the gateway.</para>

</appendix>


<appendix>
<title>Using the fake SMS center</title>

	<para>Fakesmsc is a simple testing tool to test out Kannel and
	its SMS services. It <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> be used to
	send messages to mobile terminals, it is just a simulated SMS
	center with no connection to real terminals.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Setting up fakesmsc</title>

    <para>This section sums up needed steps to set up system for
    fakesmsc use.</para>


<sect2>
<title>Compiling fakesmsc</title>

     <para>The fake SMS center should compile at the same time as main
     Kannel compiles. The outcoming binary,
     <literal>fakesmsc</literal>, is in <literal>test</literal>
     directory. The source code is quite simple and trivial, and is
     easily edited.</para>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Configuring Kannel</title>

     <para>To use <literal>fakesmsc</literal> to test out Kannel, you
     have to add it to main configuration file (see above). The
     simplest form for this configuration group is like this:</para>

<programlisting>
group = smsc
smsc = fake
host = localhost
port = 10000
</programlisting>

      <para>The fakesmsc configuration group accepts all common 'smsc' 
      configuration group variables, like <literal>smsc-id</literal>,
      <literal>preferred-smsc-id</literal> or
      <literal>denied-smsc-id</literal>, which can be used to test out
      routing systems and diverted services, before setting up real
      SMS center connections.</para>

      <para>To set up multiple fakesmsc'es, just add new
      groups. Remember to put different port number to each one.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Running Kannel with fakesmsc connections</title>

      <para>After configuring Kannel, you can start testing
      it. Remember that you HAVE to start all fakesmsc programs before
      starting the bearerbox.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Starting fake SMS center</title>

    <para>Each fakesmsc is started from command line, with all sent
    messages after command name. If any options are used (see below),
    they are put between messages and command. The usage is as
    follows:</para>

<programlisting>
test/fakesmsc [options] &lt;message1&gt; [message2 ...]
</programlisting>

    <para>Options and messages are explained below, but as fast
    example, a typical startup can go like this:</para>

<programlisting>
test/fakesmsc -p 10001 -i 0.1 -m 100 "100 200 nop" "100 300 echo this"
</programlisting>

    <para>This starts fakesmsc in port 10001, with hundred messages to
    be sent with interval of 0.1 seconds. Each message is from number
    100, and is ether to number 200 with message 'nop' or to 300 with
    message 'echo this'.</para>


<sect3>
<title>Fake messages</title>

    <para>Each message consists of three parts: sender number,
    receiver number and message itself. Sender and receiver number
    does not mean anything except for log files and number-based
    routing in Kannel. Message itself is the keyword and parameters
    then parsed in smsbox.</para>

    <para>Each part in message is separated with space. As message is
    taken as one argument, it must be put in quotation marks.</para>

    <para>If multiple messages are given, fakesmsc randomly chooses
    one for each sending.</para>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Fakesmsc command line options</title>

   <para>Fake SMS center can be started with various optional command
   line arguments.</para>

 <table frame=none>
  <title>Fakesmsc command line options</title>
  <tgroup cols=3>
  <thead>
   <row>
     <entry>Switch</entry>
     <entry>Value</entry>
     <entry>Description</entry>
   </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <row><entry><literal>-p</literal></entry>
     <entry><emphasis>port</emphasis></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Use port number <emphasis>port</emphasis> instead of default
       10000.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>-i</literal></entry>
     <entry><emphasis>interval</emphasis></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Use message interval <emphasis>interval</emphasis> (in seconds,
       fractions accepted) instead of default interval 1.0 seconds.
     </entry></row>

   <row><entry><literal>-m</literal></entry>
     <entry><emphasis>mex</emphasis></entry>
     <entry valign=bottom>
       Send maximum of <emphasis>max</emphasis> messages. Value 0
       means that infinite number of messages is sent. Default 0.
     </entry></row>
  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>

    <para>In addition, fakesmsc accepts all common Kannel <xref
    linkend="arguments" endterm="arguments.title"> like 
    <literal>--verbosity</literal>.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>
</sect1>

</appendix>


<appendix>
<title>Setting up a dial-up line</title>

	<para>This appendix explains how to set up a dial-up line for
	use with the gateway. It will probably be very short, and refer
	to existing documentation.</para>

</appendix>


</book>
